Finding aid to the Voices of Feminism Oral History Project oral histories SSC.MS.00535
Sophia Smith Collection
- Luz Rodriguez interviewed by Joyce Follet, June 16-17, 2006; Rodriguez, Luz, 1956-; Follet, Joyce (Box 45)
  Rodriguez defines herself as a servant-leader. She has continued to combine grassroots social justice work with administrative leadership in nonprofit organizations, including Henry Street Settlement, Lower East Side Family Resource Center, Dominican Women's Development Center, and Casa Atabex. In 1996 she became Executive Director of the Latina Roundtable on Health and Reproductive Rights and played a critical role in the formation of the SisterSong Women of Color Reproductive Health Collective. A specialist in organizational development and non-profit sustainability, Rodriguez currently serves as bilingual training coordinator at the New York City headquarters of the Foundation Center.
  Rodriguez was awarded a Windcall Residency in 1994 for her advocacy work. She is a published poet as well as a playwright and an aspiring sculptor. She remains active in SisterSong. She has two sons, a stepson, a foster daughter, a kinship foster child, and four grandchildren.
  Rodriguez describes childhood and adolescence on the Lower East Side. Her story underscores the centrality of cultural programs to community organizing in the late 1960s and the difficulty of integrating artistic work and political conviction in later years. Rodriguez describes the organizational challenges and personal costs involved in creating and sustaining small social justice organizations. The interview includes a detailed account of the formation of SisterSong. (Transcript 77 pp.)
  The Luz Rodriguez Papers are available for research at Smith College Special Collections.
- Catherine Roma interviewed by Joyce Follet, June 19-20, 2005; Roma, Catherine; Follet, Joyce (Box 46)
  Catherine Roma was born in Philadelphia on January 29, 1948, the youngest of three children of Italian-born parents. Her mother completed high school and, once married, was a community volunteer. Her father graduated from Princeton University and Temple Law School, but when his own father died young, he left legal practice to run the family's barber shops in Philadelphia and other East Coast railroad terminals. Practicing Catholics, Catherine's parents sent her to Germantown Friends School K-12; she remains a Convinced Friend. In the late 1960s and early 1970s, Roma earned a BA in music and an MM in Choral Conducting at the University of Wisconsin-Madison, where she became involved in socialist-feminist politics and began organizing a feminist choral group in 1974. Returning to Philadelphia the following year to teach music at Abington Friends School, she organized and conducted Anna Crusis, the first feminist women's choir in the US. In 1983 she undertook the doctorate in musical arts at the University of Cincinnati, where she founded MUSE, the community chorus she continues to lead.
  Under Roma's leadership, MUSE is a vital group in what has become a national and international grassroots movement of women's choruses. MUSE is recognized as a model anti-racist community organization and a progressive force in Cincinnati politics. According to the group's mission statement, MUSE is "a women's choir dedicated to musical excellence and social change. In keeping with our belief that diversity is strength, we are feminist women of varied ages, races, and ethnicities with a range of musical abilities, political interests, and life experiences. We are women loving women; we are heterosexual, lesbian and bisexual women united in song. We commission and seek out music composed by women, pieces written to enhance the sound of women's voices, and songs that honor the enduring spirit of all peoples. In performing, we strive for a concert experience that entertains, inspires, motivates, heals, and creates a feeling of community with our audience."
  Roma currently chairs the music department at Wilmington College. In addition to serving as Artistic Director of MUSE, Roma is founder and director of UMOJA Men's Chorus at Warren Correctional Institution, Minister of Music at St. John's Unitarian Church, and co-founder and director of the Martin Luther King Coalition Chorale. Roma and Dorothy Smith, an archivist, have been partners for many years.
  Roma recounts her childhood in Philadelphia with emphasis on the importance of her Quaker education. The oral history is a detailed example of building community through music as Roma describes her thirty years of experience in directing women's community choruses as intentional sites of creating anti-racist feminist politics through recruitment of members, decision-making process, musical repertoire and arrangement, performance venue and style, engagement of contemporary social issues, and sustained collaborations with musicians of color, especially Bernice Johnson Reagon. Roma also included six music CDs in her donation. (Transcript 118 pp.)
  The MUSE Records are available for research at Smith College Special Collections.
- Loretta Ross interviewed by Joyce Follet, November 3-5, 2004, December 1-3, 2004, and February 4, 2005; Ross, Loretta J.; Follet, Joyce (Box 47, Box 48)
  At the request of the narrator, portions of this interview are closed until January 1, 2020. A redacted transcript is available online and in the reading room.
  Loretta Ross was born in Temple, Texas, August 16, 1953, the sixth of eight children in a blended family. Her mother, who brought five older children to her marriage with Ross, had been owner of a music store and a domestic worker; she was a housewife as Loretta was growing up. Loretta's father, who hailed from Jamaica, was an Army weapons specialist and drill sergeant. After retiring from the military in 1963, he worked for the Post Office and often held additional jobs to support the family.
  Loretta attended integrated schools - Army schools through second grade, then public schools. She was double-promoted in elementary grades and was an honors student in high school. When Loretta was 11 years old, a stranger beat and raped her. At age 15 she was the victim of incest by a distant relative; she gave birth to a son, Howard, in April, 1969. Because she chose to keep her child, she lost a scholarship to Radcliffe College.
  Soon after enrolling at Howard University in 1970, Ross became involved in black nationalist politics and tenant organizing in Washington, D.C. She joined the D.C. Study Group, a Marxist-Leninist discussion group, and the South Africa Support Project. She became a founder of the National Black United Front and an officer of the City Wide Housing Coalition (1974-80). The murder of her friend and political colleague Yulanda Ward in November, 1980, which she considers a political assassination, is a turning point in her life.
  After being sterilized by use of the Dalkon Shield at the age of 23, Ross found her way to reproductive rights and anti-violence activism. She became one of the first women to win a suit against A.H. Robins, manufacturer of the device. In 1979 she became director of the D.C. Rape Crisis Center, the only center at the time run primarily by and for women of color. In that capacity she organized the first National Conference on Third World Women and Violence in 1980. While serving as Director of Women of Color Programs for the National Organization for Women (1985-89), she organized women of color delegations for the pro-choice marches NOW sponsored in 1986 and 1989, and organized the first national conference on Women of Color and Reproductive Rights in 1987. In response to the Supreme Court's Webster decision in 1989, Ross co-coordinated production of the pathbreaking statement "We Remember: African American Women Are For Reproductive Freedom." As Program Director for the National Black Women's Health Project (1989-90), she coordinated the first national conference of African American women for reproductive rights. From 1980 to 1988, she was a member of the D.C. Commission on Women.
  From 1991 to 1995, Ross was National Program Research Director for the Center for Democratic Renewal (formerly the National Anti-Klan Network), where she directed projects on right-wing organizations in South Africa, Klan and neo-Nazi involvement in anti-abortion violence, and human rights education in the U.S. In 1996 she created the National Center for Human Rights Education, a training and resource center for grassroots activists aimed at applying a human rights analysis to injustices in the U.S.
  Active internationally, Ross is a founding member of the International Council of African Women and of the Network of East-West Women. She has been a regular participant in International Women and Health Meetings and helped organize the delegation of 1100 African American women to the 1985 United Nations women's conference in Nairobi. She also participated in the UN women's women's conferences in Copenhagen in 1980 and Beijing in 1995, as well as the International Conference on Population and Development in Cairo in 1994.
  Ross has served on numerous boards (including National Women's Health Network, SisterLove Women's AIDS Project, Men Stopping Violence) and testifies on women's health and civil rights issues before Congress and the UN as well as via such national media as the Donahue Show and Pacifica News Service. She publishes on the history of abortion in the black community and is co-author of Undivided Rights: Women of Color Organize for Reproductive Justice (2004).
  Ross was co-director for women of color for the April 2004 March for Women's Lives. In January 2005, she became National Coordinator of the SisterSong Women of Color Reproductive Health Collective, a growing network of Native American, Latina, African American, Asian American and other women of color groups. SisterSong's mission is to connect reproductive rights to human rights. SisterSong promotes reproductive justice through a combination of the Self-Help approach to internalized oppression and the human rights approach to structural inequality.
  Ross completed a bachelor's degree at Agnes Scott College in 2006 and plans to enroll in a women's studies graduate program at Emory University in the fall of 2007.
  In this lengthy interview, Ross details her childhood and early education, family life and sexual assault. She traces and analyzes her political evolution from black nationalism in the 1970s to liberal feminism in the 1980s, and from human rights advocacy in the 1990s to reproductive justice organizing in the present. Her account sheds light on the interplay of national and international events in women of color organizing in the U.S. (Transcript 364 pp.)
  The Loretta Ross Papers; the Black Women's Health Imperative Records; the National Women's Health Network Records; the SisterSong: Women of Color Reproductive Justice Collective Records; and the Undivided Rights Book Project Records are available for research at Smith College Special Collections.
- Maura Russell interviewed by Kathleen Banks Nutter, June 17, 2010; Russell, Maura; Nutter, Kathleen Banks (Box 48a)
  At the request of the narrator, this interview is closed except with permission from Maura Russell until August 31, 2019.
  Maura Russell was born in 1954 in Gardner, MA, where she grew up as the oldest of eight children. Her father was the Superintendent of Schools and her mother was Director of Religious Education for their parish; both parents earned advanced degrees. She became politically active at a relatively early age, starting with the 1970 Robert Drinan campaign for the US Senate, followed by involvement in the 1972 McGovern presidential campaign and the 1983 Mel King mayoral campaign in Boston.
  In 1972 Russell entered Smith College, where she worked various factory and food service jobs while going to school, and she was involved in founding the Smith College Women's Center. Before starting her senior year, she left college to work as a welder in a Rhode Island shipyard for a year. She returned to Smith and continued to work part-time as a welder. She earned her BA in Government in 1977.
  Russell entered a union plumbing apprenticeship program in Boston in 1979. In We'll Call You If We Need You (1999), Susan Eisenberg includes some of Russell's experiences as an apprentice, many of which were difficult as Russell and a handful of other women attempted to break the gender barrier in the building trades. She owned her own residential plumbing and heating company from 1983 to 1999, fulfilling her goal of mentoring women who worked with her as apprentices. She was involved with and founded or co-founded several organizations aimed at supporting women in the building trades, up to and including a six-year stint (2000-2006) as Executive Director of Women in the Building Trades, whose records are at the Sophia Smith Collection. She is currently an Educational Specialist in the Career/Vocational Technical Office at the Massachusetts Department of Elementary and Secondary Education.
  Russell has long been involved with several community groups, in particular City Life/Vida Urbana, a grassroots organization founded in Jamaica Plain in 1973 which, according to its Web site, remains "committed to fighting for racial, social, and economic justice and gender equality…." Since 2008, much of City Life's focus has been on helping homeowners fight eviction notices. Russell has been on the Board since 1997 and is currently Board president.
  Maura and Stephanie Yesner have been together for 31 years. They married in 2004.
  Much of Maura Russell's interview focuses on the challenges she faced entering the building trades and the work she has done to help other women secure and retain employment as tradeswomen. Also of interest is her story of coming out at Smith College and the hostility she encountered from other students and college administrators. Russell also discusses the shift in her activism over the years from electoral politics to community organizing. (Transcript 69 pp.)
  The Women in the Building Trades Records are available for research at Smith College Special Collections.
- Peggy Saika interviewed by Loretta Ross, February 20, 2006; Saika, Peggy, 1945-; Ross, Loretta J. (Box 49)
  Peggy Saika was born February 26, 1945, in an Arizona internment camp. Her Japanese American family settled in Sacramento after the war. Peggy was the youngest of five children in a working-class, Buddhist family. Her father, Fred Taro Saika, was a farmworker; her mother, Dorothy Fukushima, worked in canneries and cleaned houses. After high school Peggy worked as a hairdresser while earning an undergraduate degree at Sacramento State College. She later earned a master's degree in social work.
  In the late 1960s and early 1970s, Saika was involved in left study groups and in Asian American and multiracial community activism for education, immigrant, tenant, and labor rights in Sacramento. She became coordinator of Asian Community Services. Encounters with sex discrimination in employment, an abortion experience, and an abusive personal relationship attuned Saika to women's issues as well. While living in New York City from 1978 to 1983, she worked at the Chinatown Health Center and was active in Bronx Women Against Rape (WAR), the Organization of Asian Women (OAW), and third world women's activism.
  Since returning to the Bay Area in 1983, Saika has continued to combine employment in nonprofits with community activism. From 1983 to 1991 she served as executive director of the Asian Law Caucus. In 1986 she became the first Asian American appointed to the Alameda County Commission on the Status of Women. She was a co-founder of the Asian Women's Shelter, the first shelter for abused Asian women in northern California, and in 1989 she helped organize Asian Pacific Islanders for Choice (APIC). From 1993 to 2000 Saika served as founding executive director of the Asian Pacific Environmental Network (APEN). After attending the 1995 UN Women's Conference in Beijing, she participated in creating the National Asian Pacific American Women's Forum (NAPAWF). Since 2002 Saika has been executive director of Asian Americans/Pacific Islanders in Philanthropy (AAPIP). She is active in the Buena Vista United Methodist Church.
  Saika has served on several boards, including the Ms. Foundation for Women, the California Wellness Foundation, the New World Foundation, and Choice USA. Saika is married to Art Chen, a political activist and physician. They have two children.
  In this oral history, Saika underscores the lasting impact of the internment experience as a call to vigilance and action. She traces her political involvements from pan-Asian student activism in the late 1960s forward, marking her journey through various forms of organizing: direct service, civil rights, community organizing, and philanthropy. The interview offers a general outline of Saika's path as a postwar progressive who embraces her generation's challenge to build an ethnic movement that affirms Asian American identity and rights while it also advances a broad anti-racist, feminist, class-conscious social justice agenda. (Transcript 55 pp).
- Graciela Sanchez interviewed by Loretta Ross, February 22-23, 2005; Sanchez, Graciela, 1960-; Ross, Loretta J. (Box 50)
  Graciela Sánchez was born April 24, 1960, in San Antonio, Texas, the fifth of six children of Enrique and Isabel Sánchez. She was influenced by her parents' involvement in the Chicano pride movement that began in San Antonio in the late 1960s. After graduating from Yale University in 1982, Sánchez returned to her childhood neighborhood on the near west side of San Antonio, where she remains a dedicated community organizer.
  In the 1980s, Sánchez worked with the Southwest Voter Registration Project, the Mexican American Legal Defense and Education Fund (MALDEF), and Chicana Health Policy Development. She participated in Central American solidarity work and studied filmmaking at the Escuela Internacionale de Cine y Television in Cuba. She has produced several films, including Testimonios de Nicaragua on the Sandinista Revolution and No porque lo dice Fidel Castro on lesbian and gay politics in Cuba. As an organizer in the queer community, she became a founding board member of the San Antonio Lesbian Gay assembly, the San Antonio Lesbian/Gay Media Project, and ELLAS, a state and local Latina lesbian organization.
  In 1987 Sánchez joined other women in founding the Esperanza Peace and Justice Center, which she still directs. A cultural arts and education center, Esperanza is led by lesbians of color committed to bringing grassroots and internationalist Chicana, gender, and working class perspectives together in social justice activism. The Center nurtures the arts as cultural activism and supports MujerArtes, a clay collective that has reestablished pottery-making among low-income Mexican American women as an expression of culturally-grounded empowerment. Esperanza also integrates the collecting of Chicana history into its popular education programs and serves as a repository of artifacts and resources on Mexican American women's history, including the works of Sandra Cisneros and Gloria Anzaldúa. Esperanza regularly publishes La Voz de Esperanza, which celebrates the achievements of the Chicano community with an emphasis on women. Sánchez received the Stonewall Award in 1992 in national recognition of her work in promoting lesbian rights.
  In this oral history, Sánchez describes her childhood in a close-knit extended, egalitarian working-class family, noting especially her mother's influence on her core values. She recounts her political development and activity at Yale, the difficulty of her coming out process, and her involvement in Chicano organizing projects and filmmaking. Sánchez details the development of the Esperanza Center, including the political and funding challenges of sustaining a multi-issue organization led by lesbians of color. She offers a vivid account of Esperanza's grassroots "Todos Somos Esperanza" campaign against right-wing attacks, including the Center's successful lawsuit against the city's efforts to defund it in the late 1990s. Her account of the centrality of the arts and community history to Esperanza's goals and organizing strategies is especially strong. (Transcript 106 pp.)
  At the request of the narrator, portions of this interview were restricted until September 1, 2015.
  Although this restriction has now expired, only a redacted version of the transcript remains avialble online. Please contact Special Collections for access to the unredacted version.
- Miriam Schneir interviewed by Kate Weigand, May 21–22, 2004; Schneir, Miriam, 1933-; Weigand, Kate (Box 51)
  At the request of the narrator, a portion of this interview (page 46 of the final transcript, 11:40-12:20 of tape 4) is closed until the earlier of two events: the publication of the book discussed, or Schneir's death.
  Miriam Schneir (b. 1933) grew up in New York City. A 1955 graduate of Queens College, she worked as an early childhood educator before she became a full-time writer. Schneir co-authored with her husband, Walter Schneir, Invitation to an Inquest (1965), which exposed the injustices in the Julius and Ethel Rosenberg case. Her anthology Feminism: The Essential Historical Writings (1972) was a pioneering contribution to the discipline of women's history. In Feminism in Our Time: The Essential Writings, World War II to the Present (1994), Schneir collected and published important texts from feminism's second wave which document the movement's breadth and diversity.
  In this oral history Miriam Schneir describes her childhood in an upwardly mobile New York Jewish family and her experiences in the left wing environments of Antioch College and New York City in the conservative 1950s. The interview focuses on her political awakening in the 1950s, her research on the Rosenberg case, her personal and professional connections with a variety of well-known progressive activists and feminists, and the ways she both shaped and was shaped by the feminist movement. Schneir's story details the overlapping personal and political networks that fed the emerging women's movement and illustrates the contributions made by women who were outside the conventional liberal/radical feminist divide. (Transcript 67 pp.)
- Martha Shelley interviewed by Kelly Anderson, October 12, 2003; Shelley, Martha, 1943-; Anderson, Kelly (Box 52)
  Martha Shelley (b. 1943) was born and raised in Brooklyn, New York, in a progressive Jewish home. Her mother was an illegal immigrant and worked in garment factories; her father was a machinist and accounting clerk. Martha graduated from City College in 1965, did clerking and typesetting until the mid-1980s; and is now a writer and medical/legal researcher for disability cases. The civil rights and antiwar movements radicalized Martha; her feminist activism began in 1967 with the Daughters of Bilitis, in which she was president of the New York chapter. In the 1970s Martha was involved with Gay Liberation Front, Radicalesbians, and RAT newspaper. She also produced lesbian feminist radio for WBAI and ran the Women's Press Collective. Her early political writings - "Gay is Good" and "Notes of a Radical Lesbian"- are well known and are collected in anthologies such as Sisterhood is Powerful. Shelley is also the author of Crossing the DMZ, a collection of her poetry, and Haggadah: A Celebration of Freedom. Martha Shelley currently lives in Oakland, California.